<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations upon retirement from the world Occasioned by a discourse with a gentleman, who begun to see the vanity of worldly enjoyments, whereof he had had a very great share, and thought it necessary by despising of them, to secure the interest of his soul, while there was any time left.</title>
            <author>Ludolf, Heinrich Wilhelm, 1655-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32793</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1928:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations upon retirement from the world Occasioned by a discourse with a gentleman, who begun to see the vanity of worldly enjoyments, whereof he had had a very great share, and thought it necessary by despising of them, to secure the interest of his soul, while there was any time left.</title>
                  <author>Ludolf, Heinrich Wilhelm, 1655-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed anno Dom. M D CXCI [1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at foot of [A4]: May first. Heinrich Wilhelm Ludolf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32793:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS UPON RETIREMENT FROM THE WORLD.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned By a Diſcourſe with a Gentleman, Who begun to ſee the vanity of Worldly enjoyments, whereof he had had a very great ſhare, and thought it neceſſary by deſpiſing of them, to ſecure the intereſt of his Soul, while there was any time left.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Bleſſed are they that forſake the World for Heaven, but more bleſſed are they that find Heaven, before they go out of the World.</p>
               <p>There is no more difference between Heaven and the Kingdom of God, than there is between Hell and the Kingdom of Darkneſs.</p>
               <p>Heaven conſiſts, in Vertue, Truth and Light. Hell conſiſts in Vice, Lies, and Darkneſs</p>
               <p>Our Saviour leads us the way to Heaven, and the Devil directs people to Hell.</p>
               <p>The Reader may conſider which of theſe two he had beſt to follow.</p>
            </q>
            <p>SOLI DEO GLORIA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> MDCXCI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32793:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32793:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS ROYAL-HIGHNESS Prince GEORGE OF DENMARK.</head>
            <p>THE nearer you are to Crown and Scepter, the more regard you ought to have to Him, whoſe Vicegerents, Kings and Princes are. By your indifferency about Worldly Affairs, Providence hath diſpoſed you, to deſpiſe the World, and to give your Heart to God, who hath unimaginable hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and contentment ready for thoſe, that with an intire Reſignation comply with his Will. If the following Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations have ſuch an effect upon your Mind, as to ſtrengthen your Love to the Ruler of all Hearts, He will never let you want thoſe Affections of the People, which mark and ſupport a Princes greatneſs, and I ſhall certainly ſee my Wiſhes and Hopes of the growth and continuance of your Proſperity fulfilled. When you ſee theſe preſent Broils of <hi>Europe</hi> make way for great changes in Church and State, remember this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and believe that God will reſcue thoſe that fear, love and truſt him, and that you are One of the few great Ones, not to be touched by the general Calamity, which the unuſual Earth-Quakes and other Signs of Gods Anger do forebode. Then I ſhall not ſcruple to make my ſelf known to you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32793:3"/>
            <head>READER.</head>
            <p>ALL thoſe render no ſmall ſervice to God and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that endeavour to help true Chriſtianity to get upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt. For we would ſoon have a better Church and State, if Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were thoroughly perſwaded, that real Proſperity upon Earth depended upon our Care for Heaven: This ſingle Notion well fixed in the generality of minds, would quench many a deſire by Factions to diſturb the Peace and quiet of the Nation, or to hinder its welfare by cheating the Publick, both of its Treaſure and of thoſe Services, which People leſs wedded to luxury and private intereſt might ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. How far the following Meditations may tend this way, the Chriſtian Reader will judge, who will I hope allow of my Apology for the Stile, when I tell him it is not my Native Language. I hope theſe Meditations will not have the misfortune to fall into the hands of any, that either think God a ſlave to the courſe and Laws of Nature, or that fancy, their Wiſdome above Gods Endowments. For ſuch People will conclude me as great an <hi>Euthaſiaſt</hi> as they are either Beaſts or Fooliſh-Wiſemen. It is my comfort that I have Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of my Behaviour in the greateſt adverſity, when I had the fate of the Moneyleſs, to be diſowned almoſt by every body, and ſome thought they diſcharged the duty of Friendſhip in deſiring the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Congregation, that my health and underſtanding might be reſtored to me. People that do not know of this, will hardly own me a fit Preacher of the obligation of an intire Reſignation to Gods will, if they ſhould ſee me by a wonderfull Providence rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make ſome Figure in the World. But as God alone knows how much I have been humbled, ſo it is in his only Breaſt how for I ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>May <hi>Firſt. Heinrich Wilhelm Lud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lf.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>The firſt of</hi> July, <hi>thou ſhalt have a Commentary.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="meditation">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32793:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MEDITATION</hi> I.</head>
            <p>THe World is an imperious Miſtreſs, who makes thoſe moſt uneaſie that are fondeſt of her. Which hath induced ſeveral to prefer Retirement before Greatneſs and Splendor in the World, after they have found the emptyneſs of all thoſe things, which men commonly make their Idols. Providence having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived it ſo wiſely, that whoſoever hath a wrong aim in point of happineſs, is ſooner or latter made ſenſible of his having miſſed the mark: All the miſchief cometh from miſplacing our affections, and from not beſtowing a true value upon the things we are in purſuit after. If we remembred the, <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> we would ſoon find fullfilled the, <hi>All things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Since a hearty concern for a future Life, would make us look with ſo much contempt upon the trifles of this World, that we would hardly ever diſquiet our ſelves with the deſire of any thing, that is not added to us already. But ſuch a Reſignation to Providence requireth perhaps more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion than is commonly met with in men. However we all pretend to reaſon, and thoſe that are not totally deprived of the right uſe of reaſon, will own that they have an immortal Soul, and that conſequently the ſecuring Eternity to the Soul, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the moſt important buſineſs, but that without the hopes of it, our mind will not be free from grudgings very injurious to its quiet and contentment, which influences the health of our Body very much. So that reaſon ſhould tell every man, he muſt look after Heaven, if he will enjoy happineſs upon Earth, which cannot ſubſiſt, without health in the Body and tranquility in the Mind. Gods goodneſs as well as wiſdom having ordered it ſo, that the intereſt of Body, Mind, and Soul is ſo cloſely united to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that a concern for the Soul brings us to the obſerving of our Saviours Rules, and practiſing of thoſe vertues, whereby the vigour of our Body and the contentment of our Minds is promoted; and on the other hand, managing the Body according to the Precepts of Temperance and Sobriety, ſtrengthens our Underſtanding, and inables it to deſcry in Nature and Providence, thoſe glorious Beams of Wiſdome and Goodneſs, which cannot choſe but inflame our deſires of obtaining the favour of that infinite perfect Being Which deſire, if it be ſincere and earneſt, is half way towards our Souls home. This conſideration alone ſhould be enough to keep any rational man from beſtowing any more value upon the Goods and Pleaſures of this World, than is conſiſtent with a due care of the next. Which if they did, they would not be weary of Earth before they are fitted for Heaven, and even Earthly pleaſures of Body as well as of mind, would be more real, more laſting, and more eaſily attained. They would not be at a loſs where to find retirement and quiet. For in my opinion it is not changing of City or Court for the Country, wherein a quiet Retirement conſiſts, becauſe in the greateſt Solitude, and moſt concealed Receſs our mind may be hurried about with reſtleſs paſſions and deſires; on the other hand, neither the noiſe of the City nor the hurry of the Court, can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe a temper well ſettled by not depending upon uncertainties, but intirely rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Gods Providence, which deſigns nothing but good for us. Though it cannot be denyed, that every body is not ſtrong enough to reſiſt the temptations of City and Court, which wheedle us into wrong courſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="meditation">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32793:4"/>
            <head>MEDITATION <hi>II.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce then Retirement, which is to ſet our mind at eaſe doth not conſiſt in the bare changing of the place of our abode; it ſeems to me, that the ſecret of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying quiet and tranquillity of mind, conſiſts only in withdrawing our-heart from any thing we are in poſſeſſion of in this World. This is the way to hold Riches, and Honour, nay even that more valuable pleaſure of friendſhip, without the uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fearing to loſe them, or grieving for them, when they give us the ſlip. It is a common obſervation, that Sin and Folly differ but very little, and that the Wiſdome of Providence hath put a ſtraight connexion between Sin and Puniſhment. So that whoſoever forgets his duty to his Creator to ſuch a degree, as to lay him by for the Creature, and to beſtow upon the Creature thoſe affections, which were due only to the Creator; that perſon muſt needs expoſe himſelf to a great many inconveniencies, which by Gods unchangeable Law attend the committing of Sin and Folly. We daily ſee that Wiſe-men make themſelves ridiculous about thoſe Worldly objects, which they moſt dote upon, and never make a worſe uſe of their underſtanding, than when they are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied about the things they love beſt. Love, as well as other paſſions, leading common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their Miſtreſs the Reaſon, by the noſe; and the Proverb, <hi>Love is Blind,</hi> is of a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger extent, than to be underſtood only of admiring a Woman. For we ſee Parents, fond of their Children, not only over-value their parts, but by too much indulgence to the humour of their Children, to expoſe themſelves to the juſt cenſures of diſcreet impartial perſons. We meet with bookiſh men puffed up with ſome Philological remarks, that are hiſſed at by men of ſence, and of uſe to either Church or State. Children and Books are queſtionleſs as harmleſs objects of our fancy as any, and yet when our heart is ſet upon them, they eaſily betray our folly, and bring no leſs an inconvenience upon us, than the leſſening of our reputation by having our judgement called in queſtion. As ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational loving of ſenſual pleaſures, Money and Fame is more criminal, ſo it is attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with puniſhment more real, than the bare loſs of the good opinion of men of ſence. I do not ſpeak only of men that purſue theſe things by the commiſſion of the moſt provoking ſins, but even of thoſe that hunt after them in ſome ſeeming honeſt courſe. A man may endeavour to grow rich, without Robbing and Cheating, another may offer at Greatneſs without Slandering or Supplanting, and yet both theſe men will find themſelves miſtaken at the long run, if they make this their chief buſineſs, and it is a Mercy of God, when he ſhews them their error, and directs them to look after that which muſt render the injoyment of plenty and greatneſs ſecure and comfortable. This cannot be obtained unleſs a body be ſure of Gods favor and ſupport, but it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that God Almighty will aſſure a man of ſo great a bleſſing, unleſs he thinks it worth the longing for it, which he is not like to do, as long as his mind chiefly runs upon worldly things. Wherefore I conclude that withdrawing our heart from worldly things, is the true retirement, which leads us to calmneſs of mind, and keeps us from being diſturbed, in the City and Court as well as in the Country. Nay it will beget that love and truſt in God, which makes Proſperity the more comfortable and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the leſs uneaſie, and when our croſſes ſeem to overballance too much our comforts, this ſort of Retirement will make us amends for all, by a promiſing proſpect of our future hopes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="meditation">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32793:4"/>
            <head>MEDITATION <hi>III.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is, I muſt confeſs, not ſo very eaſie, to withdraw our heart from the world; for it is hard to blot out the impreſſions made upon our minds in our younger years. One that alwayes heard people admired for a great Eſtate, for a ſplendid Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping and magnificent Furniture and Retinue, will be backward to believe that all thoſe things ſignifie nothing, and are not worth our ſeeking them. We hear Great Men ſo often reckoned among the fortunate, and very often ſee ſo many real advantages of power, that we cannot help almoſt our being betrayed into Ambition. Nay when bountiful Nature hath beſtowed ſo good an underſtanding upon us, as to be convinced, that Wealth and Greatneſs are very empty things without Contentedneſs, there is one object left, from which it is hardeſt of all to withdraw our heart, <hi>that is, We our ſelves;</hi> The wiſe Author of Nature hath implanted in us a love of our being, that we might ſeek to preſerve, and to improve it: And there is no queſtion to be made, but that it would ſtand us in very great ſtead, if we loved our ſelves with a due regard to our glorious <hi>Maker,</hi> for it is more than probable that our <hi>Being</hi> may be improved by him, that contrived it ſo artificially. But when we lay him a ſide, and perhaps do every thing to affront him into the bargain, it is no wonder he ſhould revenge ſo baſe an ingratitude, by ſuffering our <hi>Self love</hi> to lead us as a blind Guide. This perverſe <hi>Self love</hi> begets that uncharitableneſs and envy, from whence ſprings all the ſtrife and faction, which diſturbs ſo very much both publick and private. It intoxicates us with that conceit of our own judgment, that we will hardly allow any body to be in the right but our ſelves, making commonly very peeviſh requitals to thoſe that offer to ſhew us our miſtakes. In one word <hi>Self-love</hi> is the root of Pride, which is ſo criminal a qualification, that it turned <hi>Lucifer</hi> out of Heaven. The inlightened Author of <hi>The Whole Duty Man,</hi> makes very good Remarks upon this ſubject. Nor can it be denyed that the greater the thing is which we are proud of, the greater is our Sin and conſequently the Fall that attends Pride commonly. The miſchief of our being pleaſed with our own perſon is not ſo great, as to think our judgment infallible; and being puffed up with a vain conceit of Saintſhip, is worſe ſtill, and very often occaſions thoſe falſe lights, whereby many a poor ſoul is lead into precipices. The reaſon ſeems to be, that Pride hath ingratitude towards God Almighty at the bottom, for the proud man doth not reflect upon his holding every thing of God Almighty, and the greater his gifts are, the greater is his ingratitude, when he aſcribes them to himſelf. Since then <hi>Self-love</hi> is ſo dangerous, and yet ſo natural to us, we ought to take the more particular care to break ourſelves of that fondneſs of our ſelves, which is the laſt and hardeſt difficulty to be overcome by one, who would fain injoy that Retirement, wherein we are paſt being diſpleaſed with any thing but what diſpleaſes God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="meditation">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:32793:5"/>
            <head>MEDITATION <hi>IV.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SUCH a diſengagement of our hearts from all worldly affections fits us for that love of God, whereby we endear our ſelves to him, and receive thoſe returns from him, which bring us to ſo much experience of his mercy, that we never deſpond even under the worſt circumſtances, but bear the worſt lot of his Providence without reluctancy. It would be ſtrange if God Almighty, who hath given ſo innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable proofs of his goodneſs towards us, ſhould look with indifferency upon thoſe that endeavour to anſwer his deſign in creating of Man, and endowing him with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. If we think we have reaſon to leſſen our kindneſs for a perſon, which doth love another beſides us. How can we imagine, that Infinite Being ſhould take it well at our hands, when we kindly entertain ſo deſpicable Rivals beſides him. Many pious perſons hold, that God created Man only for a witneſs to his wonders, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and injoy the beauty of the whole Creation; and after Man had by his ingratitude, forfeited ſo great a bliſs, and by his diſobedience brought the ſad puniſhment upon him, which hath made his Poſterity ſmart ever ſince; Yet God was pleaſed to give ſtill a greater proof of his Love in pittying Mans deplorable condition, and providing a mean for its relief. What is not ſuch an Infinite Goodneſs like to do for one, who is ſenſible of ſo unſpeakable a Mercy, and with a due acknowledgement of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs makes it his utmoſt care to pleaſe his Creator. If we make never ſo few Chriſtian Reflexions upon the courſe he takes with us, we will ſoon find that he courts us for our heart, by all the methods imaginable, and when they do not prevail, he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitters the enjoyment of thoſe very things which inticed our heart away from him. He doth not deſerve ſo great a favour as affliction, that doth not look upon it, as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of God Almighty to wean us from thoſe things which rendered us treacherous to him. Our mind muſt have ſome thing to delight chiefly in, and which way ſoever it inclines, there it ſticks cloſer and cloſer. If it bend towards the world, it will intangle it ſelf faſter and faſter in it, and remove further and further from God. But if our mind fix once upon God, it will deſpiſe the world more and more, and grow in delighting in God Almighty and Heaven. The more our love tends this way, the more our expectations will be anſwered. Till by degrees it bring us to ſo ſtraight a union with God, that no Temptation will tear us from him. When God once finds us true to him, he gives us thoſe aſſurances of his being true to us, that nothing is able to ſhake us, or to grieve us; till at length we arrive at ſuch an intimacy with him, as to have no other will but his, and to bear with an intire reſignation his diſpoſals. Then we begin to ſee wonders of Wiſedome, Goodneſs, Mercy and Juſtice, even in thoſe Events. which the world thinks chance, and we will find that the more we ſeek Heaven the more we find happineſs upon Earth, whereas ſeeking the Trifles of the Earth makes us loſe Heaven and doth nothing but inbroil us here upon earth. So that in my opinion it is Prudence as well as Religion, to give our Heart to God and not to the World, than I am ſure the Vanity of the World will never make us uneaſie, nor puzzle us where to find that tranquillity and cherfullneſs of mind, which ſweetens this life and gives us a foretaſte of that which is to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="meditation">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32793:5"/>
            <head>MEDITATION <hi>V.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr fear any body ſhould think theſe Notions inſignificant whims of my own brains. I adviſe to examine, whether they are not agreeable to what was ſaid before by one, whoſe Wiſdom and Truth no Chriſtian can have an exception to, There is ſcarce another ſence to be given to thoſe words of our Saviours, whereby he declared, <hi>That the Love of his Heavenly Father was not in us, as long as we loved the, World.</hi> But if people will not mind his Doctrine, how can they wonder at their not finding the Truth and Benefit of it. Withdrawing our heart from the World, and giving it to God, is that forſaking of every thing, which hath the promiſe of an hundred fold recompence. Whereof no body is like to gain a fortunate experience that doth not think it worth his while to attempt a trial of it. Though I am of opinion the truth of my Notions will be called in queſtion by no body who owns the Bible to contain Gods Word. The number indeed of thoſe is far greater, which think it beneath them to ſubmit their underſtanding to Gods Wiſdome, not to ſpeak of thoſe, which count <hi>David</hi> a fool, for calling thoſe Fools, which denyed a God. I will not now incroach upon the province of Divines, and threaten thoſe Sparks with the heavy Judgments, that are like to befal them, or think ſo meanly of my time, as to go about the prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their errors, ſince they admit only of heatheniſh arguments, they may go; thoſe paſſages in <hi>Seneca,</hi> which make Contempt of Riches the great Road towards becoming Rich. And they may learn of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that ſince mans happineſs conſiſts in pleaſure he muſt needs be moſt happy, whoſe pleaſure is leaſt ſubject to uncertainty, or to taſte as much of Gall as of Hony. My Meditations being deſigned only for the improvement of Chriſtianity. I dare aſſure my ſelf, that any perſon, who will earneſtly endeavour for Chriſts ſake to forſake his Life, will by Gods bleſſing find a far better. I have not been yet in the other World, and cannot ſpeak by experience of what we have to expect there. But I know that forſaking of thoſe courſes which ſet us at a greater and greater diſtance from God, will bring us by degrees to ſuch a life here upon Earth, which is not only free from diſquiet, and fear, but wherein natural pleaſures are eaſie, and even the thought of their loſs moſt pleaſant. I ſhall never be perſwaded to embrace the ſottiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of thoſe, that ſuppoſe all the pleaſures of the body, were by the bountiful Creator of the Univerſe, laid only as ſo many ſnares for our Soul, and upon that account deny their bodies not only recreation but neceſſaries. It is too low a fancy to imagine that ſo infinite a goodneſs as that of the Almighty can take delight in making us uneaſie, and I have reaſon to believe, that the infinite liberality of our Creator deſireth nothing of us but a grateful injoyment of what is given, being ſo free to grant the deſires of thoſe that love him, that they can ſcarce thank him heartily for a mercy received, before there is a greater one ready. Though I am afraid there is not over many that have had a full ſence hereof, ſince there is ſo few, that think it worth their while by a real hearty Contempt of the World to offer at a little more familiar acquaintance with Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. My Meditations do not belong to thoſe that had rather live like Beaſts than Men, but thoſe that pay ſome reſpects to Reaſon and Chriſtianity, will be backward to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn me too raſhly for an <hi>Enthuſiast,</hi> eſpecially if they do not meaſure other peoples Corn with their own Buſhel, but have humility enough to ſuppoſe, that by others they may be exceeded in Vertue as well as in Vice, and that conſequently they muſt not think themſelves in poſſeſſion of the greateſt ſhare, of thoſe Bleſſings, which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Vertue and Piety, in this Life as well as in the next.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="meditation">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32793:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MEDITATION</hi> VI.</head>
            <p>THis new Life, which it is no paradox to call the beginning of the Eternal one, is ſo unſpeakable a happineſs, that no body ought to grudge forſaking the Old one, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſo contemptible an opinion of, that he did not think it worth the name of Life, when he deſired to be delivered of the body of this death. I can give ſo far an experimental deſcription of it, that it puts a period to thoſe unfortunate jarrings between the <hi>Paſſions, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> which ſo deſperately diſturb a man in the Old life, and all our Faculties within us, do in the new Life their parts with ſuch a ſweet harmony, that Reaſon commands our Appetite and Paſſions with ſuch an abſolute, and yet very indulgent ſway, that both Appetite and Paſſions, afford nothing but Pleaſure, and ſuch a Pleaſure, which leaves no ſting behind but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes with the injoyment. Reaſon on the other hand acts with that humble regard to the Divine Majeſty, from whence it had its ſpring, that it willingly by Faith ſubmits to thoſe unſearchable Myſteries, which muſt of neceſſity be far above an underſtanding, darkened by the general corruption of Mankind. But the more we endeavour by the grace of God to free our ſelves from that corruption, the more that veil of the eyes of our underſtandings will fall off, and by degrees God Almighty enables us to ſee, that <hi>Faith</hi> is no intollerable Miſtreſs to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but that the perfection of <hi>Reaſon</hi> conſiſts, in being convinced of, and in underſtanding the Truth and Reality of Divine Myſteries. It is true, it would be great preſumption in any man by his own forces to recover that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which was forfeited by his Primogenitors ingratitude; But ſince Gods infinite mercy hath provided the mean of our Mediator for our Reſtauration, it is the greateſt wonder to me, that there can be ſuch wretches, as to neglect and mock that, for which no humane tongue or underſtanding can find proportionate thanks. I muſt confeſs the generality of Chriſtians, is ſo little behind hand with the <hi>Jews</hi> in deſpiſing of our Saviour, that they boggle as much as the <hi>Jews</hi> at the truth of our Saviours aſſeveration, <hi>That, no body ever ſhould ſee death that kept his Sayings.</hi> But how can any body be inabled to keep thoſe Sayings or Commandments, if he will not take his refuge to him, whoſe Merit and Interceſſion muſt procure us the neceſſary help for it Since then Eternal Life, or the beginning thereof, a New Life here upon earth, can be attained to, only by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts Saying, or by following of his Example, it is abſolutely neceſſary, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to deſire, and earneſtly to attempt the practice of thoſe Vertues which Chriſt reckoned our bleſſedneſs, and made them the Subject of all his diſcourſes, though he knew the World ſuch a ſtranger to them, that he thought it neceſſary to beſpeak their attention by Similitudes and Parables. I will not waſte Time and Paper in ſumming up and deſcribing the Lovelineſs and Uſefulneſs of thoſe Vertues, the Practice whereof is, that <hi>Keeping of Chriſts Commandments,</hi> which he takes as a ſign of our belief in, and love of him, for which he hath promiſed ſo unimaginable a Reward, that God will love us, come to us and make his abode with us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. Thoſe that think our Saviour too plain in recommending of thoſe Vertues, may read the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> where they are treated of more methodically, and in a ſtile more ſutable to the faſhion of theſe times. But I am afraid there is ſuch a proud ſtubborn Generation, which would hardly hear one ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to ſpeak of GODS WILL, though he ſhould comply with all the faſhions of the World, that are not directly oppoſite to the will of God. For I believe they would think him as far from being a Prophet, becauſe he appeared among the wicked, as the old Prophets were contemned for flying from the wickedneſs of the World. But God will confound the vain conceit of the World, by not confining his Providence to the notions of humane Wiſdome.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="meditation">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32793:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MEDITATION</hi> VII.</head>
            <p>THE damned Pride of humane Wiſedom is indeed come to that paſs, that People will hardly allow the <hi>Almighties Prorogative</hi> by his uncontroulable Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to manage this World. We have a daily experience of Gods diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the ſubtlety of Mens deſigns, and of embroiling that ſucceſs of the crafty, which Gods unſearchable counſel permits ſometimes. And yet we are generally ſo far from reflecting more upon God than upon our own brains, that we fancy we are able to baffle the diſpoſals of Infinite Power, which I am afraid hath connived long enough to convince us of his extraordinary Mercy, and to keep us from thinking thoſe judgements too ſevere, which it ſeems begin to come upon Earth, and which will very heavily light upon thoſe heads, that have hitherto laughed at the threatnings of <hi>Gods Word.</hi> It is not my task by theſe Meditations to explain the firſt part of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> and to determine what way and how ſoon here upon Earth as well as in Heaven; <hi>Gods Name</hi> is to be hallowed, <hi>Gods Kingdom</hi> to come, and <hi>Gods will to be done.</hi> Thoſe that mind our Saviours Exhortations, will not neglect to endeavour the being in a readineſs for it at all times. Gods mercy hath nevertheleſs extended ſo far as to raiſe of late perſons, underſtanding thoſe dark Paſſages both of the Old and New Teſtament, which ſpeak of the Triumph of goodneſs over wickedneſs. I have ſeen onely ſome writings of Mrs. <hi>Bourignon</hi> and Mr. <hi>Poiret,</hi> but I know there is more perſons acquainted with the nearneſs of that time. But I perceive there is ſcarce any more heed taken of what they ſay or Write, than of <hi>Noah</hi> before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge. It is an unaccountable thing that even thoſe, which own the Bible to come from God, ſhould leſs reflect upon what is contained in it about an univerſal Reign of Juſtice, Peace and Joy; than upon the tricks of the Devil, to turn that Reign into ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule by ſome Millenarians, ſome Quakers, and ſome Family of Love Men. We are queſtionleſs too preſumptuous of ourſelves, if we ſuppoſe there was no need of our Saviour for warning us againſt the fierceneſs and cheats of the Devil in the latter times. But our Saviours Doctrine is grown ſo deſpicable with the far greater part, that it is thought below a Wit, either to hold that our Saviour is God, or to believe that there is a Devil.</p>
            <p>But Great God have thou in thy infinite Mercy a tender compaſſion of thy poor people in this laſt and moſt furious aſſault of the Adverſary, hear the ſighs of thoſe that groan under his Tyranny, and prepare thoſe that fear thee, for thy appearence which thou wilt ſhortly make to avenge the Scorn of thy Onely Son, ſtrengthen the Faith of thoſe thou thinkeſt fit to bring to the fiery Trial, and do not defer long mercifully to fullfil thy decrees about me; for my Redeemers ſake.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
